Finding Aid for the Jan Williams Collection of Annotated Scores, 1950-1999
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Jan Williams Collection of Annotated Scores 1950-1999
Mus. Arc. 10.1
Williams, Jan, 1939-
15 boxes (224 items)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Scores owned by percussionist and conductor, Jan Williams. The majority of the scores were marked by Williams for use in performance. Some scores bear inscriptions from composers to Williams.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jan Willams, 1994.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Jan Gardner Williams was born July 17, 1939 in Utica, New York. He earned his Bachelor's and Master's Degrees in Music at Manhattan School of Music where he studied percussion with Paul Price and he was a member of the American Symphony Orchestra 1962-1964 under conductor Leopold Stokowski. Williams was selected as one of the first class of Creative Associates for the Center of the Creative and Performing Arts in 1964 at the University at Buffalo. He remained at the University at Buffalo where he created the University at Buffalo Percussion Ensemble in 1964, was appointed to the Music Faculty in 1967, served as Chair of the Music Department 1981-1984, and retired in 1996. He also served as artistic director of the Center of the Creative and Performing Arts 1974-1979 and as its resident conductor 1976-1980. He co-directed the North American New Music Festival with Yvar Mikhashoff 1983-1991.
Jan Williams has performed as solo percussionist with orchestras in Paris, Berlin, Israel, Detroit, New York, and Copenhagen. He has appeared as percussionist, conductor, and instructor throughout the United States and internationally. Composers who have written works for him include John Cage, Elliott Carter, Joel Chadabe, Luis De Pablo, Gustavo Matamoros, Frederic Rzewski, Iannis Xenakis, Morton Feldman, Orlando Garcia, Nils Vigeland, and Lukas Foss. His playing and conducting has been captured on at least three dozen commercial recordings and hundreds of archival recordings.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains two hundred sixteen music scores owned by percussionist and conductor Jan Williams. The majority of the scores, chiefly from the 1950s to 1990s, contain markings by Williams (and others) for performing the compositions. While some of the performance markings are negligible, others constitute full realizations of aleatoric compositions. In some cases only handwritten notes indicate how a composition was to be performed.
Arrangement
The collection is basically arranged in alphabetical order by composer name and then by title, with some exceptions.
Container List
- Albright, William Tic: a spectacle for two groups of performers, soloist, films, and tape / William Albright. [1967?], 1 ms. score ([1] leaf) + 6 ms. parts; 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 1)
  Holograph (Ozalid reproduction). Cover title. For any combination of the following: 2 pianos, 2 amplified guitars, 2 percussionists, 2 string basses, and 2 voices. Graphic notation. Duration: 11:46.
- Amy, Gilbert Inventions, instrumental ensemble [Inventions I-II / Gilbert Amy]. [1965?], 1 ms. score (29, 13 leaves); 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 2)
  Ms. (Ink on vellum). For flute, piano/celesta, harp, and vibraphone/marimba. Lacking "Interludes pour harpe" to be played between Inventions I and II; also lacking p.30-39 of the Heugel published score (1964).
- Austin, Larry Life pulse music Charles Ives' life pulse music: for percussion orchestra. / Larry Austin [S.l., 1984], 1 ms. score (90 p.); 37 cm. (Box 1, Item 3)
  Holograph (Photocopy). "Realization drawn from Ives' sketches for his Universe Symphony." Use of multi-track cue tape is strongly recommended by the composer. At end: 2/2/84. Denton, TX. Marked for performance by percussionist and conductor, Jan Williams.
- Austin, Larry Life pulse prelude. Snare drum cycles Snare drum cycles: from the Life pulse prelude / Larry Austin Baltimore,: Smith Publications, c1987., 1 score (4 p.); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 4)
  For solo snare drum. "Based on sketches and plans for percussion orchestra music from a portion of Charles Ives's unfinished Universe Symphony." Inscription on title page. from the composer to Jan Williams.
- Bergamo, John Haiku Five Haiku: for young voices and chamber orchestra / by John Bergamo. [1964], 1 ms. score (16 p.); 33 cm. (Box 1, Item 5)
  Holograph (Photocopy). For mixed voices (SATB), percussion (4 players), and piano. Instrumentation page indicates parts for Violins 1 and 2, Flute, and Bb clarinet, but no parts for them identified in score. At end of score: "Buffalo, November 10, 1964." Marked for performance by percussionist, conductor Jan Williams.
- Bergamo, John Shradhanjali: percussion solo with percussion ensemble / by John Bergamo. [1964], 1 ms. score ([5] leaves); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 6)
  Holograph (Photocopy). Score consists of written, prose instructions. Includes extra copy of instructions. Marked for performance by percussionist, conductor Jan Williams.
- Bergamo, John Tanka / John Bergamo. 1964., 1 ms. score (17 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 7)
  Holograph (Ozalid copy). Caption title. For solo percussion. At end: March 5, 1964. Marked for performance by percussionist, Jan Williams.
- Berlioz, Hector, 1803-1869 Symphonie fantastique. March to the scaffold; arr. March to the scaffold: from the "Fantastic symphony" / Hector Berlioz; arranged for percussion ensemble by Harold Farberman New York, N.Y.: Cortelu Pub. Co., 1983., 1 score (16 p.) + 10 parts; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 8)
  Arranged for percussion ensemble by Harold Farberman Inscribed by the arranger.
- Bertoncini, Mario, 1932- Tune: per x serie di 5 piatti sospesi / Mario Bertoncini. 1965., 1 score (3 leaves); 33 x 46 cm. (Box 1, Item 9)
  Holograph (Ozalid copy). Caption title. "Rome, 15 ottobre 1965"--Caption. Marked for performance by percussionist, Jan Williams. Performance instructions in Italian ([4] leaves) inserted.
- Boone, Charles Lightfall: [for] solo snare drum / Charles Boone. 1989., 2 leaves of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 10)
  Caption title. Holograph (Photocopy). Score consists of typed, numerical patterns. Performance instructions and personal note from composer to percussionist, Jan Williams, inserted.
- Boone, Charles Watts towers: for solo drummer / Charles Boone. [1959-1999], [6] ms. leaves of music; 26 x 33 cm. (Box 1, Item 11)
  Ms. (Photocopy). Caption title. For one percussionist playing "an array of six drums: concert bongos, tomtoms, snares (snares off), floor tomtoms, etc." Duration: 8:00. Leaves mounted on cardboard backing. Marked for performance by percussionist, Jan Williams.
- Boulez, Pierre, 1925- Pli selon pli. Improvisation sur Mallarmé, no. 1 Improvisation sur Mallarmé: le vierge, le vivace et le bel aujourd'hui / Pierre Boulez [Wien: Universal Edition, c1958], 2 scores (24 p. each); 24 cm. (Box 2, Item 12)
  For soprano, harp, vibraphone, bells, and percussion (4 players). Two photocopies of Universal Edition score (pl. no. U.E. 12855 LW) marked as percussion parts, cut and pasted onto cardboard backings. Prepared by John Bergamo. Acc. by personal note (3 ms. pages) from Bergamo to Jan Williams. Duration: 06:00.
- Brewaeys, Luc Sig-mords: for solo percussion: opus 40 / L. Brewaeys. [1980?], 11 ms. leaves of music; 30 cm. (Box 2, Item 13)
  Holograph (Photocopy). At end of score: 13-11-80. Inscription on title page. from the composer. Marked for performance.
- Brown, Earle, 1926-2002 Calder piece: for 4 percussionists and mobile / Earle Brown. [1965-1966], 1 ms. score (7 leaves); 29 x 44 cm. (Box 2, Item 14)
  Holograph (Photocopy). Caption title. For 4 percussionists, performed with mobile by Alexander Calder. Marked for performance by percussionist, Jan Williams.
- Brown, Earle, 1926-2002 Folio, no. 2. Selections [Folio II / Earle Brown]. [1980-1994], [3] leaves of ms. music; 21-35 cm. (Box 2, Item 15)
  Holographs (Photocopies). For indeterminate instrumentation. Graphic notation. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. Includes ms. note (1 leaf) by Eberhard Blum about performance of "for Ann" and additional, unmarked photocopy of same work.
- Brown, Earle, 1926-2002 Folio, no. 2. Selections Folio II: after 1970 / [Earle Brown]. [1980-1994], [5] leaves of ms. music; 21 x 28 cm. (Box 2, Item 16)
  Holographs (Photocopies). Title from leaf 1 of "Remarks for performers." Graphic notation. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Brown, Earle, 1926-2002 Hodograph, no. 1 Hodograph 1 / Earle Brown New York: Associated Music Publishers, c1961., 1 ms. score (8 leaves); 37 cm. (Box 2, Item 17)
  Holograph (Photocopy). For flute, piano, celeste, orchestral bells, Vibraphone, and marimba (3 players). At end of score: June 1959 N.Y.C. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Burge, David, 1930- Sources, no. 3 Sources III: for two performers (clarinet and percussion) / David Burge [S.l.]: Tetra Music Corp. ;New York, N.Y.: Sole selling agent: A. Broude, c1968., 1 score (3 folded leaves); 46 cm. (Box 2, Item 18)
  Performance score. Reproduced from holograph. At end of score: "January 25, 1967 Boulder, Colorado." Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Burritt, Michael Sticks of eloquence: for multiple percussion solo / Michael Burritt Cleveland, Ohio (557 E. 140th St., Cleveland 44110-1999): Ludwig Music, c1987., 7 p. of music; 28 cm. (Box 2, Item 19)
  Inscribed by the composer.
- Bussotti, Sylvano Fogli. Coeur Sette fogli: una collezione occulta.[Coeur] / Sylvano Bussotti [London: Universal Edition, c1963], 1 folder ([5] leaves); 28 cm. (Box 2, Item 20)
  Title from caption on instruction sheet. Consists of: photocopies of performance instructions (1 leaf) and score (1 leaf) from Universal Edition (pl. no. 13238) publication; photocopy of same score marked in preparation for realization; score realized by Jan Williams (1 folded leaf, April 2001); and 1 leaf of pencil ms. notes by Jan Williams. Graphic notation.
- Cage, John Atlas eclipticalis / John Cage New York: Henmar Press: C.F. Peters, c1961., 1 part (4 p.); 30 x 45 cm. (Box 2, Item 21)
  "Instrumental parts to be played in whole or part in any ensemble, chamber or orchestral, with or without Winter music." Percussion I part, reproduced from holograph. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Cage, John Composed improvisation, snare drum C: composed improvisation: for snare drum / John Cage [S.l.]: Henmar, c1987., 2 p. of music; 28 cm. (Box 2, Item 22)
  Score consists of performance instructions. Includes realization (1991) by percussionist Jan Williams: list of instruments (1 leaf); 5 leaves ms. notes; realization (3 ms. leaves plus 1 photocopy of same leaves), amplifier operator score (1 ms. leaf; 1 typescript leaf plus photocopy of same leaf).
- Cage, John Music for ...: parts for flute, clarinet, trombone, three percussion, piano, violin, and cello without score (no fixed relation), title to be completed by adding to "Music for"--The number of players performing / John Cage New York: Henmar Press: Sole selling agents: C.F. Peters, c1984., 1 part (6 leaves); 36 cm. (Box 2, Item 23)
  Cover title. Percussion I part. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. Includes published performance instructions and additional notes by Jan Williams (1 ms. leaf).Photocopy.
- Cage, John Music for ...: parts for voice and instruments without score (no fixed relation), title to be completed by adding to "Music for"--The number of players performing / John Cage New York: Henmar Press: [Sole selling agents, C.F. Peters], c1984, [1987], 1 part (6 leaves); 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 24)
  Percussion IV part. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. Includes published performance instructions, additional notes by Jan Williams (7 ms. leaves), and additional photocopy of leaves 1-4 of the part (also marked).Photocopy.
- Cage, John Music for ...: parts for voice and instruments without score (no fixed relation), title to be completed by adding to "Music for"--The number of players performing / John Cage New York: Henmar Press: [Sole selling agents, C.F. Peters], c1984, [1987], 1 part (6 leaves); 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 25)
  Percussion IV part. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. Includes published performance instructions. Photocopy.
- Cage, John Ryoanji / John Cage [New York: Henmar Press, c1983], 1 part ([2] leaves); 28 cm. (Box 2, Item 26)
  Caption title. Printed part of ensemble player A. "At least two only slightly resonant instruments of different material (wood and metal, not metal and metal) played in unison"--Leaf [2]. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. Includes 2nd photocopy of part (21 cm.).Photocopy.
- Cage, John She is asleep. Quartet She is asleep. Quartet, 12 tom toms / John Cage New York, N.Y.: Henmar Press, c1960., 6 scores (6 p. each); 30 cm. (Box 2, Item 27)
  For 4 players, 3 tom toms each graduated in pitch. "Edition Peters"--Cover. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. Includes additional photocopy of score.
- Cage, John 27'10.544" 27'10.544": for a percussionist / John Cage New York, N.Y.: Henmar Press, c1960., 28 p. of music; 22 x 33 cm. (Box 2, Item 28)
  Reproduced from holograph. Photocopied clippings which make reference to Marcel Duchamp are taped into the score at various places. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Cage, John Variations, no. 3 [Variations III / John Cage] New York: Henmar Press, c1963., 1 folder ([5] leaves, 1 envelope); 33 cm. (Box 2, Item 29)
  Lacking score; contains published performance instructions, 1 envelope of circles on transparencies, [4] leaves of notes for realization by Jan Williams (4/13/95). For one or any number of people performing any actions.
- Carter, Elliott, 1908- Pieces, timpani Eight pieces: for four timpani (one player) / Elliott Carter New York: Associated Music, c1968., 23 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 30)
  Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams; some pages duplicated to ease page-turning.
- Carter, Elliott, 1908- Pieces, timpani Eight pieces: for four timpani (one player) / Elliott Carter New York: Associated Music, c1968., 23 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 31)
  Inscription on title page. from the composer to percussionist Jan Williams.
- Carter, Elliott, 1908- Pieces, timpani Eight pieces: for four timpani (one player) / Elliott Carter New York: Associated Music, c1968., 23 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 32)
  Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Carter, Elliott, 1908- Pieces, timpani. Selections [Eight pieces for four timpani: revised score / Elliott Carter]. [1966], [9], 2, 2 leaves of ms. music; 32-37 cm. (Box 2, Item 33)
  Holograph (Ozalid copy). Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams, with markings by the composer.
- Carter, Elliott, 1908- Pieces, timpani. Recitative Recitative and improvisation: for four kettledrums (one player) / Elliott Carter New York: Associated Music, c1960., 7 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 34)
  Both movements incorporated into Eight pieces for timpani in 1968 published score. Duration: 6:45. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Carter, Elliott, 1908- Pieces, timpani. Recitative Recitative and improvisation: for four kettledrums (one player) / Elliott Carter New York: Associated Music, c1960., 7 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 35)
  Both movements incorporated into Eight pieces for timpani in 1968 published score. Duration: 6:45. Typescript notes (1 leaf) by the composer inserted. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Carter, Elliott, 1908- Pieces, timpani. Selections Six pieces: for kettledrums (4): 1950 / Elliott Carter. 1950., 11 leaves of ms. music; 36 cm. (Box 2, Item 36)
  Holograph (Photocopy). For one percussionist. At end: Tucson, Nov. 1950. "Property of Paul Price"--stamp on title page., crossed out. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Chadabe, Joel Echoes: for percussion and electronics / Joel Chadabe. [1972], 1 ms. score (3 leaves); 24 x 28 cm. (Box 3, Item 37)
  Holograph (Photocopy). For percussionist and assistant with microphone; or with accompanying pre-recorded tape of echoes. Graphic notation. At end of score: Albany, 9/2/72. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. Typescript performance instructions (1 leaf, photocopied) inserted.
- Chadabe, Joel Flyby / Joel Chadabe. [1991], 1 ms. leaf; 28 cm. (Box 3, Item 38)
  Ms. notes by Jan Williams in preparation for April 20, 1991 performance of work for percussion and MIDI electronics at North American New Music Festival.
- Chadabe, Joel Follow me softly / Chadabe. [1984], 3 ms. leaves; 28 cm. (Box 3, Item 39)
  Caption title. Ms. notes by Jan Williams in preparation for April 12, 1984 performance of work for percussion at North American New Music Festival.
- Chadabe, Joel Rhythms: for percussion and computer / Joel Chadabe. c1980., 1 ms. score ([7] leaves); 30 cm. (Box 3, Item 40)
  Caption title. Manuscript. "The percussionist may accompany, be accompanied by, complement and/or articulate rhythms generated by, or improvise melodies with, the computer"--Instructions. Includes performance instructions and description of one realization by Jan Williams. Another copy of realization (3 leaves) laid in container.
- Chadabe, Joel Round trip / Chadabe. [1992], 1 ms. leaf; 28 cm. (Box 3, Item 41)
  Caption title. Ms. notes by Jan Williams in preparation for April 5, 1992 performance of work for percussion and computer at North American New Music Festival.
- Colgrass, Michael Light spirit / by Michael Colgrass. 1963., 1 ms. part (10 p.); 36 cm. (Box 3, Item 42)
  Holograph (Ozalid copy) Percussion I and II part. Cover title. For flute, viola, guitar, and percussion, 2 players. Performance instructions on verso of cover. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Crumb, George Madrigals, book 1 Madrigals: book I for soprano, vibraphone, and contrabass / George Crumb [S.l., 1965], 1 ms. score (6 p.); 28 x 39 cm. (Box 3, Item 43)
  Caption title. Reproduced from ms. Spanish words and phonetics; text from poems by Federico García Lorca; also printed as texts with English translations. Includes performance instructions. "The 4 books of Lorca madrigals may be performed: (a) as separate works ... (b) as a larger cycle in which the 4 books are played in sequence"--Performance notes. At end: 1965 Buffalo, N.Y. Marked for performance (minimally) by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Di Pietro, Rocco Melodia Nera: (1980-1982): timpani solo / Rocco Di Pietro Lancaster, NY (P.O. Box 436, Lancaster, NY 14086): A.M. Percussion Publications, c1985., 5 p. of music; 28 cm. (Box 3, Item 44)
  Includes performance instructions. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. Inscription on title page. from the composer to Jan and Diane Williams.
- Di Pietro, Rocco Overture, organ, synthesizer, percussion Overture: [for] percussion orchestra / Rocco Di Pietro. [1980], 1 ms. score (8 leaves); 49 cm. (Box 3, Item 45)
  Reproduced from holograph. Handwritten emendations by the composer. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. "[For] percussion orchestra, organ and synthesizer"--Caption. At end: November- Fine- December 1980 R.D.P. Handwritten quotations from Richard Wagner and Luigi Russolo on l. 1A.
- Di Pietro, Rocco. Overture, organ, synthesizer, percussion Overture to Combats for history: per gruppi di percussione, organo e sintetizzante = [for] percussion orchestra, organ and synthesizer instruments / Rocco Di Pietro. [1980], 1 ms. score ([9] leaves); 49 cm. (Box 3, Item 45a)
  Holograph (Ozalid reproduction). Caption title. Original title blacked out: Overature. "For Jan Williams"--At top of page. "For percussion orchestra - 80 instruments in six groups - 12-15 players"--Caption. Prefatory leaf contains lists of percussion instruments in six groups. Changes to sectional durations changed on leaf [8]; prefatory leaf marked by percussionist Jan Williams with list of instruments needed to acquire. At end of score: November- Fine- December 1980 R.D.P.
- Di Pietro, Rocco Popular songs Three popular songs: per soprano, pianoforte e percussione (1984); op. 74 no. 1 / Rocco Di Pietro; di testi su Luis A. Rosario Quiles, Bertolt Brecht, e Allen Pettersson. [1984], 1 ms. score (3 leaves); 35 x 57 cm. (Box 3, Item 46)
  Caption title. Reproduced from holograph. For soprano, piano, and percussion. English words. At end: May 27, 1984. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Dubrovay, László, 1943- Duos, violin, percussion Sei duo: per violino e percussioni / Dubrovay László Budapest: Editio Musica, 1971., 1 score (7 p.); 34 cm. (Box 3, Item 47)
  Duration: about 7 min. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968 La mariée mise à par ses cé libataires même / Marcel Duchamp; realization by Petr Kotík, 1974., 1 ms. score (28 leaves); 29 x 45 cm. (Box 3, Item 48)
  Photocopy of Kotík holograph. Title from added title page. For alto flute, celeste, trombone, glockenspiel, and marimba. At end: October 22, 1974. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams.
- Felder, David Lines from twenty poems Three lines from twenty poems: for chamber orchestra / David Felder. 1987, c1986., 1 ms. score (26 p.); 43 cm. (Box 3, Item 49)
  For tape and orchestra: 1_2_1_1_/1121/timp, perc(2)/hrp/pno/str (6-6-5-5-4). Based on the writings of Pablo Neruda. Reproduced from signed holograph. Duration: ca. 8:45. "Commissioned by the Research Foundation of S.U.N.Y. with the assistance of the Jory Fund of the American Music Center." Marked for performance by conductor Jan Williams.
- Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987 Crippled symmetry / Morton Feldman. 1983., 1 score (38 leaves); 37 cm. (Box 3, Item 50)
  Holograph (Ozalid copy). For flute (bass flute), vibraphone (glockenspiel), and piano (celesta). Caption title. "C1983 Universal EDT."--Inscription bottom of leaf 1. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. "1st perf. Akademie der Künste, Berlin, Feb. 5, 1984, [Eberhard] Blum, [Nils] Vigeland, [Jan] Williams"--Bottom of leaf 1.
- Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987 For Philip Guston / Morton Feldman. c1985., 1 ms. score (102 p.); 44 cm. (Box 3, Item 51)
  Holograph (Ozalid copy). For flute (piccolo, alto flute), percussion (1 player, including vibraphone, glockenspiel, chimes, marimba), and piano (celesta). Caption title. "C1984 Universal EDT"--Bottom of p. 1. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. Score disbound; individual sheets re-ordered, and some duplicated, to facilitate page-turning. At end of score: Nov. 9, 1984.
- Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987 Instruments, no. 1 Instruments: [I] / Morton Feldman. c1974., 1 ms. score (9 leaves); 37 cm. (Box 3, Item 52)
  Holograph (Ozalid copy). For alto flute, oboe, trombone, celesta and percussion. Caption title. "Commissioned by the S.E.M. Ensemble"--Caption. "Copyright Universal EDT 1974"--Bottom of leaf 1. At end of score: July 29, 1974. Marked for performance by percussionist Jan Williams. All staves of percussion part replaced with new staves on manuscript paper with notation of percussion part enlarged.
- Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987 Instruments, no. 3 Instruments III / Morton Feldman. c1977., 1 ms. score (14 leaves); 36 cm. (Box 4, Item 53)